{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "After declining an invitation from Imelda Marcos, this band was approached by mobs in\nManila. Mia Farrow accompanied this band on their trip to India to visit the Maharishi Mahesh\nYogi [mah-hah-REESH-ee mah-HESH YOH-gee]. One of this band’s members claimed that\nthey were “more popular than Jesus.” Sigmund Freud [FROYD] and Bob Dylan are among the\nmany personalities depicted on the cover of this band’s album Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club\nBand. For 10 points, name this band from Liverpool known as the “Fab Four.”",
      "answer": "The Beatles"
    },
    {
      "question": "It's not the UK, but a team from this country sponsored by Emirates lost eight straight races to lose the 2013 America’s Cup. This country contests both the Bledisloe Cup and the Freedom Cup in a sport where they are represented by a team that uses a silver fern as an emblem and performs the Kapa o Pango and the Ka Mate. For 10 points, name this country whose rugby union team, the All Blacks, performs the haka, a ceremonial war dance of its indigenous Maori people.",
      "answer": "New Zealand"
    },
    {
      "question": "The characters in this novel became Japanese schoolgirls in the series Ikki Tousen, or Battle Vixens. A video game series created by Omega Force and Koei that is based on this novel lets you kill opponents to fill your musou bar to perform special attacks, and is called Dynasty Warriors. A two-part John Woo film based on this novel was entitled Red Cliff after a battle in which Cao Cao [Tsao tsao] was defeated. For 10 points, name this basis for a series of twelve tactical RPG games from Koei, a Chinese classic about the battles between the states of Eastern Wu, Cao Wei, and Shu Han.",
      "answer": "Romance of the Three Kingdoms"
    },
    {
      "question": "This singer quoted Khrushchev’s line “We will bury you!” and hoped the title people “love their children too” in his song “Russians”. He performed alongside Branford Marsalis and Phil Collins at Live Aid in 1985. More famously, he joined Andy Summers and Stewart Copeland in a band for which he sang a song inspired by Nabokov’s Lolita called “Don’t Stand So Close To Me.” For 10 points, name this man who wrote “Message in a Bottle” for the band in which he was lead singer, The Police.",
      "answer": "Sting"
    },
    {
      "question": "Marty Glickman claimed that his removal from an Olympic team in favor of this man was a political capitulation by Avery Brundage. This man provided the “greatest 45 minutes in sports” by breaking three world records and tying another at a Big Ten conference meet. This athlete controversially claimed that “it was our president who snubbed me” in response to having not shaken Adolf Hitler’s hand on the medal podium. For ten points, name this African-American runner who won four gold medals at the 1936 Summer Olympics.",
      "answer": "James Cleveland Jesse Owens"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one of these conflicts, William Eaton led an expedition to capture Derna, and one ship ran aground by William Bainbridge was burned by the crew of the USS Intrepid. The USS Philadelphia was burned in the first of these conflicts by Stephen Decatur, and Decatur’s capture of the Meshuda during the second of these wars led to peace with Tunis, Tripoli, and Algeria. For ten points, name these early 19th century wars between the United States and a group of North African states.",
      "answer": "Barbary Wars"
    },
    {
      "question": "The subject of this film was inspired by its star’s study with Roger Revelle. Oklahoma Senator Jim Inhofe compared this film to Hitler’s Mein Kampf. This film won Best Original Song for Melissa Etheridge’s“INeedtoWakeUp,”anditexplainstheKeelingCurveina“slideshow”thatshowsretreating glaciers and other damage caused by the greenhouse effect. For ten points, name this 2006 documentary in which former Vice President Al Gore gives a presentation on the dangers of global warming.",
      "answer": "An Inconvenient Truth"
    },
    {
      "question": "Leo Gorcey demanded $400 for his inclusion in this artwork. Jann Haworth and Peter Blake produced this work, which features three depictions of Shirley Temple and one of Stu Sutcliffe. Gandhi and Hitler were removed from this artwork, whose central figures wear yellow, pink, blue, and red military uniforms. Dozens of cardboard cutouts are arranged in the background of, for ten points, what artwork that was mass produced with a record that includes “A Day in the Life” and “Lucy in the Sky with Diamonds” by The Beatles?",
      "answer": "the album cover for Sgt. Pepper’s Lonely Hearts Club Band"
    },
    {
      "question": "A theme in Mozart’s twenty-fifth piano concerto is sometimes cited as this song’s source. Pyotr Lavrov wrote a “worker’s” version of this song, which was originally written by Claude Rouget de Lisle as “War Song for the Rhine Army.” A musical depiction of the Battle of Borodino juxtaposes this song with “God Save The Tsar.” This song was quoted in Tchaikovsky’s 1812 Overture, where it represents Napoleon’s army. For ten points, name this revolutionary song, the national anthem of France.",
      "answer": "La Marseillaise"
    },
    {
      "question": "One leader in these conflicts saw a vision of three suns before his victory at Mortimer’s Cross. For switching sides in these conflicts, Richard Neville, the Earl of Warwick, was known as the Kingmaker. These conflicts ended when Richard III was defeated by Henry VII at Bosworth, ushering in the Tudor dynasty. For ten points, name these conflicts between the rival English houses of Lancaster and York, named for their respective red and white flower badges.",
      "answer": "Wars of the Roses"
    },
    {
      "question": "This piece’s melody was also used for “When the Warrior Returns,” which celebrated Stephen Decatur’s victory in the Barbary Wars. The opening of this song is used to represent Lieutenant Pinkerton in Giacomo Puccini’s Madame Butterfly. The lyrics to this song were written aboard the HMS Tonnant and set to the tune of To Anacreon in Heaven. For ten points, name this patriotic song written during the defense of Fort McHenry by Francis Scott Key.",
      "answer": "The Star-Spangled Banner"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was not given songwriting credit on “Never Learn Not to Love” by the Beach Boys, even though it was derived from this man’s song “Cease to Exist.” This man’s belief in hidden messages on the Beatles’ White Album inspired the idea of a “Helter Skelter” race war. One of the stars of Valley of the Dolls, Sharon Tate, was over eight months pregnant when this man’s followers murdered her in 1969. For ten points, name this cult leader who died in prison in 2017.",
      "answer": "Charles Manson"
    },
    {
      "question": "Allison Janney earned an Oscar nomination for playing this woman’s mother, the abusive LaVona Fay Golden. This woman followed Midori Ito to become the second woman to ever land a triple axel, but became infamous when her ex-husband, Jeff Gillooly, conspired to attack her rival before the 1994 Winter Olympics. A 2017 film by Craig Gillespie stars Margot Robbie as, for ten points, what American figure skater and rival of Nancy Kerrigan?",
      "answer": [
        "Tonya Harding",
        "Tonya Maxene Price"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1971 edition of this game, success was determined by how fast and accurately they typed words like “BANG” or “WOW.” MECC produced this game, in which taking the Barlow Road or floating across the Columbia River Gorge are the two options for players as they approach Willamette Valley. The player is responsible for leading for leading a wagon party starting at Independence, Missouri in, for ten points, what classic educational computer game that shares its name with a pioneer route?",
      "answer": "The Oregon Trail"
    },
    {
      "question": "TheOfficial Bulletin wasthedailynewspaperofthisorganization,whichreleasedfilmslikePersching’s Answer. A piece created by this organization shows a gorilla holding a struggling woman and contains the caption “Destroy this Mad Brute.” Workers in this organization gave over 7.5 million speeches during the changing of film reels; those speakers were known as Four Minute Men. Posters encouraging civilians to buy liberty bonds were created by, for ten points, what committee that used propaganda to build support for American participation in World War I?",
      "answer": [
        "Creel Committee",
        "Committee On Public Information"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1947, this team’s GM Billy Evans wrote “TRUST YOU WILL FIND YOUR NEW CONNECTION A MOST PROFITABLE ONE” in an antisemitic telegram telling Jewish-American star Hank Greenberg he’d been given away to the Pittsburgh Pirates. In 1912, a player for this team shouted “I don’t care if he got no feet!” when fans tried to get him to stop beating a handicapped man who had been heckling him; that player’s career hits record was broken by Pete Rose. The notoriously racist Ty Cobb played over two decades with, for ten points, what Major League Baseball team in Michigan?",
      "answer": [
        "Detroit Tigers",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This conflict’s pivotal siege of Mahenge led the losing side to discard their castor oil and flee. During this conflict, the losing side rebeled against Carl Peters on the advice of Hongo, a snake spirit. The losers of this conflict joined Bokero after they were forced to produce cotton for export, leading to a devastating famine. For ten points, name this 1905 rebellion in German East Africa named for a medicine that was said to turn German bullets into water.",
      "answer": "Maji Maji Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "ThismanbelievedhehadkilledBernard“Lotsapoppa”Croweafterhesawanewsreportaboutadead Black Panther. This resident of the Spahn Movie Ranch was taught the guitar by Alvin “Creepy” Karpis, and he sent Bobby Beausoleil to kill music teacher Gary Hinman. Lynette “Squeaky” Fromme, a failed assassin of Gerald Ford, was a follower of this man, whose other followers carried out the Tate-LaBianca murders. The term “Helter Skelter” was used for an impending race war by, for ten points, what serial killer who led a cult in California in the 1960s?",
      "answer": "Charles Milles Manson Maddox"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man launched a series of modernizations with his Vision 2020 program. This man, a former spymaster for the Ugandan military, worked alongside Uganda’s Yoweri Museveni to fund the ADFL and topple Mobutu Sese Seko in the First Congo War. After a conflict broke out with the death of Juvenal Habyarimana, this man’s troops recaptured Kigali from the Interwanhame to end a genocide perpetrated by Hutu paramilitary groups. For ten points, name this Tutsi leader and president of Rwanda.",
      "answer": "Paul Kagame"
    },
    {
      "question": "The creator of this game series founded MicroProse in 1982, which produced products such as an historically-based game which allowed players to sail the Spanish Main as a pirate. In the 2016 release from this series, players can reveal the Hermetic Order secret society by discovering a natural wonder. That game in this series also includes a civics tree to parallel its technology tree and features novel playable factions such as the Scythians and the Hungarians. For ten points, name this strategic computer game series whose entries bear the name of creator Sid Meier.",
      "answer": [
        "Sid Meier's Civilization",
        "Sid Meier’s Civilization VI"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As a rookie, this Hall-of-Famer batted .174 [[One seventy-four]] for Kansas City. Five years later, this man won his first of three World Series in a row and was voted league MVP the following year. A teammate described this flamboyant player saying, \"There isn't enough mustard in the whole world to cover that hotdog.\" When this man retired in 1987, his 563 career home runs ranked him sixth all-time. Holding the World Series records for most runs and most homers in a single series, for ten points, who is this slugger, nicknamed “Mr. October\"?",
      "answer": "Reggie Jackson 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "After the release of this film, Canada’s Fairview Lawn Cemetery was overrun with visitors, particularly around the grave of Joseph Dawson. Six weeks after this movie’s release, seven percent of American teenage girls had seen it twice, and it made more money in its eleventh week in theaters than in its first. For ten points, name this 1997 James Cameron-directed movie, the first to ever gross more than a billion dollars, named for the title doomed ocean liner.",
      "answer": "Titanic 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this musical, one of the title characters lends a copy of Uncle Tom’s Cabin to a slave named Tuptim. Based on Margaret Landon's work of historical fiction, in this musical a widow and her son leave India for the promise of a job as a governess and a “brick house.” In one song in this musical, Anna asks the grandson of Rama I, “Shall I Tell You What I Think of You?” For ten points, in what Rodgers and Hammerstein work does Anna teach the wives and children of Mongkut, the ruler of Siam?",
      "answer": "The King and I"
    },
    {
      "question": "Toward the end of this man’s reign, a meteor was found inscribed with the prophecy of his death, leading him to kill everyone nearby. A musician who had been blinded by this ruler attempted to assassinate him with a lute which had been weighted with lead. This man was killed by another heavy metal prescribed for him by his team of alchemists as an \"Elixir of Immortality.\" For ten points, name this conqueror of Chu who became the first emperor of China.",
      "answer": [
        "Qin Shi Huang Di or Ying Zheng",
        "Zheng, King of Qin",
        "Zhao",
        "Huangdi",
        "Qin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An early lyric by this group parodies the nativist views of Enoch Powell and demands that immigrants return to their “commonwealth homes.” This group's members took an ill- fated trip to Rishikesh [[ree-shee-KESH]] for a guided meditation course with Maharishi Mahesh Yogi. A member of this group left that course early to film the documentary Raga about his sitar teacher, Ravi Shankar. For ten points, name this influential band of the British Invasion whose songs “Get Back” and “Norwegian Wood” were credited to John Lennon and Paul McCartney.",
      "answer": "The Beatles"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a 1980s dinner Nancy Reagan apocryphally asked what this man has done to be at a White House dinner, with this musician responding \" I've changed the course of music five or six times.\" With Gil Evans, this musical figure created arrangements for the George Gershwin opera, Porgy and Bess. The Birth of the Cool and Kind of Blue were albums by, for ten points, which American Jazz trumpeter of the work Miles Ahead?",
      "answer": "Miles Davis"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1970s, this man was nominated for Best Recording for Children at the Grammys for an educational album featuring [this man] and His Gang vs. Mr. Tooth Decay. Jimmy Carter tasked this athlete with a 1980 tour of Africa to endorse the boycott of the Moscow Olympics. In an effort to legitimize his regime, dictator Mobutu Sese Seko hosted a contest between this athlete and George Foreman, the so-called \"Rumble in the Jungle.\" Cassius Clay was once the name of, for ten points, which boxer, known as \"The Greatest\"?",
      "answer": [
        "Muhammad Ali",
        "Cassius Marcellus Clay Jr. before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The sancai [san-tsye] technique of three-color pottery glazing dates to this dynasty. Yang\nGuifei [yong gwee-fay], one of the Four Beauties, was the consort of this dynasty’s Emperor\nXuanzong. It was interrupted by the Second Zhou [zhoe] Dynasty of Empress Wu, and it rose to\npower after the Sui [sway] dynasty. Its first emperor was Taizong, and Li Po and Dufu were\nfamous poets who lived during this dynasty. For 10 points, name this Chinese dynasty that lasted\nfrom 618 to 907.",
        "answer": [
          "Tang Dynasty",
          "Tang",
          "Tang chao"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Tang [tong] dynasty faced this rebellion, led by a namesake general, who\nestablished the Yan dynasty.",
        "answer": [
          "An Lushan rebellion",
          "An Lushan",
          "An-shi",
          "An-shi rebellion",
          "Tianbao",
          "Tianbao rebellion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This musician was accompanied by members of the Paul Butterfield Blues Band during a\ncontroversial performance at the 1965 Newport Folk Festival in which he “went electric.”\nRolling Stone twice claimed that the greatest song of all time was the first single from this man’s\nalbum Highway 61 Revisited. For the point, name this Minnesota-born singer-songwriter of\n“Like a Rolling Stone”.",
        "answer": [
          "Bob Dylan",
          "Robert Allen Zimmerman",
          "Zimmerman"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the late 1970s, Dylan alienated many fans by performing this action, which heavily\ninfluenced the content of his albums Slow Train Coming and Saved.",
        "answer": [
          "converting to Christianity",
          "Christian",
          "becoming a born-again Christian",
          "born-again",
          "Christianity"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This team won a match referred to by their opponents as the “robbery of the century” because\nAntonio Rattin was sent off. A shot that hit the crossbar and bounced onto the goal line gave this\nteam its only World Cup victory, over West Germany in 1966. In 1950, this team suffered a\nshocking World Cup loss to the United States. For 10 points, name this national soccer team that\nplays home games at Wembley Stadium in London.",
        "answer": [
          "England",
          "English",
          "English national team",
          "Three Lions"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "England was eliminated from the 2014 World Cup after a 2-1 group stage loss to this\nteam, which both won and hosted the first World Cup in 1930.",
        "answer": [
          "Uruguay",
          "Uruguayan national team",
          "Uruguayan",
          "La Celeste",
          "Charruas"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An early battle in this conflict was the clash at Covadonga, which was a victory for the\nVisigoth Pelayo. Its turning point is usually considered the defeat of the Almohads at the 13th\ncentury Battle of Las Navas de Tolosa. The union of several factions in this conflict led to the\njoint rule of the Dual Monarchs. El Cid was a heroic figure from, for 10 points, what conflict\nconcluded by Ferdinand and Isabella that ended the period of Islamic government in Spain?",
        "answer": [
          "Reconquista of Iberia",
          "Reconquista",
          "reconquest"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The end of the Reconquista is considered to be the surrender of Granada by this man, this\nlast Muslim ruler in Iberia.",
        "answer": [
          "Muhammad XII",
          "Boabdil",
          "Abu Abdullah Muhammad XII"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman aided Richard Harman, who was arrested for smuggling illegal Tyndale Bibles.\nThis woman’s influence is credited with causing the downfall of Lord Chancellor Thomas\nWolsey. Along with musician Mark Smeaton, this niece of Thomas Howard was imprisoned in\nthe Tower of London on charges of adultery. For 10 points, name this woman executed in 1536,\nthe second wife of Henry VIII.",
        "answer": [
          "Anne Boleyn",
          "Boleyn"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Anne’s death her husband faced what Catholic rebellion based in Yorkshire and\nled by Robert Aske?",
        "answer": "Pilgrimage of Grace"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Like Hassler Whitney, this man’s work in algebraic geometry produced a namesake embedding theorem. This man lends his name to situations where no agent is better off if they are the only one to change their strategy. With Harsanyi and Selten, this mathematician won the 1994 Econ Nobel for his work in game theory. For 10 points, identify this schizophrenic subject of the movie A Beautiful Mind.",
        "answer": "John Forbes Nash, Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In some games, Nash equilibria can occur when the strategies are of what impure type, in which a player plays each move with a certain probability?",
        "answer": "mixed strategies"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One player for this team shared the 1997 MVP award with Brett Favre after rushing for 2,053 yards; that player retired in 1999, even though he was within 1,500 yards of Walter Payton’s career rushing record. In 2010, another player for this team had a touchdown overruled for not maintaining possession for the entire catch under a controversial rule now named for him. For ten points, name this NFL team, whose lack of success under ownership by the Ford family caused Barry Sanders and Calvin Johnson to announce surprisingly early retirements.",
        "answer": [
          "Detroit Lions",
          "either"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lions have won four NFL championships, though none since their 1957 victory over this team, which didn’t exist from 1996-99 when Art Modell moved the team to Baltimore, where they became the Ravens.",
        "answer": "Cleveland Browns"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While awaiting trial for his role with the Chicago Eight, Abbie Hoffman wrote about this event, including his fight with Pete Townshend. During this event, Chip Monck announced “It is suggested that you stay away from [the brown acid].” Travel mishaps prevented Iron Butterfly from attending this event, which was held at Max Yasgur’s farm, and included performances by Jefferson Airplane and The Who. Over 400,000 people attended, for ten points, what 1969 music festival in New York?",
        "answer": "Woodstock Music Festival or Woodstock Music & Art Fair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This guitarist, who died at age 27, used heavy distortion and feedback in a legendary rendition of the Star-Spangled Banner at Woodstock.",
        "answer": "Jimi Hendrix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character claims to possess an “itemized list of thirty years of disagreements” in one appearance. One character aggravatedly notes that this man wrote 51 separate essays in a work that was only supposed to run 25 total essays. This character is introduced as a “bastard orphan” in the opening song of his musical, which is narrated by his eventual assassin, Aaron Burr. For ten points, name this protagonist of a 2015 Lin-Manuel Miranda musical and first Secretary of the Treasury.",
        "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander Hamilton marries Eliza, the middle daughter of a man with this last name. A song named after Eliza and her sisters with this last name occurs in Act I of the musical.",
        "answer": "Schuyler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Newport was one attempt to end this conflict. The Engagers took part in the Putney debates and were crushed at the battle of Preston during this war. Prince Rupert of the Rhine was decisively defeated at Marston Moor during this conflict, in which Pride’s Purge abolished the Long Parliament. Thomas Fairfax at Naseby opened, for ten points, what 17th century war that pitted Oliver Cromwell and Parliament against the royal forces of King Charles I?",
        "answer": "English Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Fairfax led this Roundhead, professional military force whose cavalry was called the Ironsides.",
        "answer": "New Model Army"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side during this conflict conquered Colonia del Sacramento, but was forced to return it at the end of this conflict. The Duc de Villars won the Battle of Friedlingen during this conflict. The forces of Eugene of Savoy and the Duke of Marlborough won the Battle of Blenheim during this conflict. The Treaty of Utrecht ended, for ten points, what war that broke out in 1701 after Philip V became the king of a certain Iberian country?",
        "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Spanish Succession broke out after the death of a Spanish king with this name. Another ruler with this name was known as “El Cazador” and was forced to abdicate in 1808.",
        "answer": "Charles or Carlos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This musician wrote an acoustic song from the point of view of serial killer Charles Starkweather, and won an Oscar for his contribution to a 1993 film in which Tom Hanks plays a lawyer dying of AIDS. “Streets of Philadelphia” and “Nebraska” were written by this musician, who sang about a “long gone daddy” Vietnam vet in a song that was misinterpreted as an optimistic anthem by Ronald Reagan’s 1984 campaign. “Glory Days” and “Dancing in the Dark” were sung by, for ten points, what front man of the E Street Band, who sang “Born In The U.S.A.”?",
        "answer": "Bruce Springsteen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Democratic candidate, whose running mate was John Edwards, used Springsteen’s “No Surrender” as his campaign song – with Springsteen’s permission.",
        "answer": "John Kerry"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One member of this team was suspended six games for headbutting referee Ted Bernhardt, then another 11 games a year later for kicking a cameraman in the groin. Other players for this team included Toni Kukoc [koo-”coach”] and Luc Longley. During President Obama’s 2016 visit with the champion Warriors, he noted that one member of this team, the “greatest of all time,” was with them: coach Steve Kerr. For ten points, name this NBA team that won 72 games in 1995-96, the first year of the second “three-peat” of championships won by Phil Jackson, Scottie Pippen, and Michael Jordan.",
        "answer": [
          "Chicago Bulls",
          "either"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Hall of Fame rebounder earned the aforementioned suspensions, in addition to three rings with the Bulls. He has earned criticism for his recent “hoops diplomacy” efforts in Asia.",
        "answer": "Dennis Rodman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While playing against one team from this city in 2012, Joey Barton earned a 12-game suspension for attacking Carlos Tevez, Vincent Kompany, and Sergio Aguero. In that game, Aguero’s 94th minute goal for a team from this city defeated Queens Park Rangers to clinch a title at the expense of another team from this city. That team from this city has suffered under managers David Moyes and Louis van Gaal since the 2013 retirement of Sir Alex Ferguson. For ten points, name this English city whose rival clubs, City and United, have won fifteen of the 23 Premier League titles.",
        "answer": "Manchester"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The only teams to win an English Premier League title are the two Manchester clubs, Arsenal, Blackburn Rovers, and this club, which defended its 2015 title by falling as far as 16th in the table.",
        "answer": "Chelsea F.C."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An early action during this conflict was the capture of Government House in Stanley. This conflict began on the orders of Leopoldo Galtieri, who lost power as a result. During this war, Exocet missiles were able to destroy the Sheffield, and the Conqueror was able to sink the General Belgrano. This war’s outcome hastened the fall of a military junta while strengthening Margaret Thatcher’s government. For ten points, name this 1982 war between Argentina and Britain over a South Atlantic archipelago.",
        "answer": "Falklands War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Argentine military junta that collapsed shortly after the Falklands War came to power during this period of state terrorism in Argentina, during which the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo protested the kidnapping of “disappeared persons.”",
        "answer": [
          "Dirty War or Guerra Sucia",
          "Process of National Reorganization"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This singer collaborated with Stevie Wonder on “Ebony and Ivory” and with Michael Jackson on 1983’s “Say Say Say.” In 1984, this man convinced Michael Jackson of the benefit of owning copyrights to songs; Jackson promptly outbid this man for his own catalog of songs. In January 2017, this man sued Sony Music Publishing in another attempt to gain ownership of “The Long and Winding Road” and “Yesterday,” songs on which he shares a writing credit with John Lennon. For ten points, name this bass guitarist for the Beatles.",
        "answer": "James Paul McCartney"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "To avoid losing millions of pounds to tax, McCartney and the other Beatles founded this corporation, which published new Beatles material starting in 1968. Allen Klein’s brief leadership of this company is often cited as a contributing factor for the band’s breakup.",
        "answer": [
          "Apple Corps, Inc.",
          "Apple Publishing and/or Apple Records"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Poland was forced to exit this war following the Treaty of Altranstadt, which also provided for the execution of the nobleman Johann Patkul. Shortly after a naval engagement at Grengam, this conflict was ended through The Treaty of Nystad. During this conflict, the Cossack leader Ivan Mazepa joined forces with Charles XII, only to be defeated by the forces of Peter the Great. For ten points, name this 18th century conflict in which Russia defeated the Swedish empire.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ivan Mazepa and Charles XII alliance at this 1709 battle failed to overcome Peter the Great’s forces, and Sweden failed to recover. After this battle, Carl Gustav Rehnskiold was captured and Charles XII fled to the Ottoman Empire.",
        "answer": "Battle of Poltava"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This musician paid tribute to the head of the African National Congress in “Full Nelson.” The wife of Akhnaten lent her name to this man’s final all-acoustic album, Nefertiti, which featured Wayne Shorter and Herbie Hancock as part of his “second great quintet.” A 1957 compilation album by this man’s nonet lent its name to a genre that succeeded bebop. Birth of the Cool was performed by, for ten points, what jazz trumpeter who recorded Kind of Blue?",
        "answer": "Miles Davis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned track “Full Nelson” pays tribute to Nelson Mandela and appears on an album whose title pays tribute to this other South African human rights activist, the winner of the 1984 Nobel Peace Prize.",
        "answer": "Archbishop Desmond Mpilo Tutu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Near the end of this film, a man indicates his support for the main character by wiping the sweat off of his brow using his handkerchief. Lily James portrays a secretary in this film whose primary job is to type dictated letters and speeches. In this film, Viscount Halifax threatens to resign his cabinet position unless the Prime Minister agrees to peace talks with Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this 2017 film set in May 1940, named for a famous speech of Winston Churchill.",
        "answer": "Darkest Hour"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This legendary British actor reportedly burned through - literally - a $20,000 cigar budget while portraying Winston Churchill in Darkest Hour. This man’s past disparaging remarks about the Golden Globes didn’t prevent him from winning their Best Actor in a Drama award in 2018.",
        "answer": "Gary Oldman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first of these conflicts was triggered by crackdowns against the Gio and Mano ethnic groups. In another of these conflicts, the LURD rebel group shelled the capital until the Accra Peace Agreement was signed. The first of these conflicts led to the capture and murder of Samuel Doe, and the second led to Gyude Bryant leading a transitional government until the election of Ellen Johnson Sirleaf. Charles Taylor rose to power after the first of these wars and was exiled after the second. For ten points, name this pair of internal conflicts that rocked Monrovia.",
        "answer": [
          "Liberian Civil Wars",
          "descriptions of civil fighting in Liberia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the Second Liberian Civil War, LURD allied themselves with the Kamajors hunter unit from this country, located immediately northwest of Liberia.",
        "answer": "Sierra Leone"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While led by Donald Fehr, one of these organizations accused Peter Ueberroth of inciting collusion; that organization of this type was earlier led by Marvin Miller, who worked to nullify the reserve clause in the fight for free agency. An attempt to create one of these organizations at Northwestern University was blocked by the NLRB in 2015, and another one of these organizations was recertified by Roger Goodell after a 2011 lockout. For ten points, name these organizations that represent athletes in collective bargaining.",
        "answer": [
          "labor unions in sports",
          "answers related to professional baseball unions throughout",
          "answers related to amateur and/or college football unions after Northwestern is read",
          "answers related to professional football unions after “Goodell” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Major League Baseball’s reserve clause was challenged by Curt Flood and the union in a 1972 Supreme Court case; this justice wrote a lengthy history of baseball in the majority opinion. This man’s other majority opinions include Roe v. Wade.",
        "answer": "Harry Blackmun"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man recited the song “What Do You Do With the Mad that You Feel?” in a Congressional hearing chaired by John Pastore, who declared this man’s testimony “wonderful” and said “Looks like you just earned the $20 million.” Tom Hanks will portray this man in a 2019 film, a year after an acclaimed Morgan Neville documentary about this man became the highest-grossing biographic documentary of all time. For ten points, name this sweater-wearing late children’s television host, the subject of the films, A Beautiful Day in the Neighborhood and Won’t You Be My Neighbor?.",
        "answer": "Fred Rogers or Mister Rogers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mister Rogers’ 1969 Congressional testimony sought to reverse budget cuts made to this non-profit, which founded and funds both PBS and NPR. This corporation’s support is prominently thanked, usually before the support of “Viewers Like You,” by many PBS programs.",
        "answer": "Corporation for Public Broadcasting or CPB"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the lockout-shortened 1999 season, this team lost in the NBA Finals despite entering the playoffs as an 8 seed. This team lost the 1994 NBA Finals, and its win in Game 5 of that series was televised in a small box in the corner while the majority of the screen covered the ongoing OJ Simpson low-speed car chase. Patrick Ewing played 15 seasons for, for ten points, what NBA team that is owned by James Dolan’s Madison Square Garden Company?",
        "answer": [
          "New York Knicks",
          "either",
          "both names"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 1998-99 NBA lockout was one of four work stoppages during the tenure of this NBA commissioner, who held the job for 30 years until being succeeded by Adam Silver in 2014. Conspiracy theorists hold that this man froze the Knicks’ envelope in the 1985 Draft Lottery, helping them win the first pick to draft Patrick Ewing.",
        "answer": "David Stern"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The musicians Stobrod and Pangle are deserters from this war in a film that focuses on the love of Ada for carpenter W.P. Inman, who enlists in it. Sergio Leone’s The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly is set against the backdrop of this war, as is Cold Mountain. Denzel Washington stars as Silas Tripp in Glory, in which he takes up his regiment’s flag at the Siege of Fort Wagner during this war. For ten points, name this war, the subject of films like Andersonville and Gettysburg.",
        "answer": "US Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Andersonville and Gettysburg were produced by this Civil War buff who founded CNN.",
        "answer": "Robert Edward “Ted” Turner"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. During this conflict, panic broke out after John Feeks was killed above a watching crowd. During this conflict, engineer Harold Brown campaigned against a “danger from sudden deaths” by killing dogs in public. Anachronistic claims place the death of Topsy the Elephant during this conflict, in which one side lobbied to have the other side carry out the first execution by electric chair. For ten points, name this late 19th century “war” over the marketplace for electric power that was “lost” by Thomas Edison’s DC technology.",
        "answer": [
          "War of the Currents",
          "Battle of the Currents",
          "descriptions of the competition between AC and DC power, alternating and direct current electricity, etc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the War of the Currents, Harold Brown challenged this advocate of AC power to a “duel” in which each would be shocked by increasing amounts of their preferred form of electricity; the first to quit would have lost, but this inventor of the air brake declined the duel.",
        "answer": "George Westinghouse"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A player of this instrument collaborated on the album East Meets West with Yehudi Menuhin at the 1966 Bath Music Festival. Vilayat Khan popularized this instrument, which was played by a virtuoso at the charity Concert for Bangla Desh and taught to George Harrison for songs like “Norwegian Wood.” The score for Satyajit Ray’s Apu Trilogy was composed by Ravi Shankar, a master of, for ten points, what Hindustani string instrument?",
        "answer": "sitar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A sitar is featured in the introduction to “Paint it Black” by this British rock band. This band’s performance at the Altamont Free Concert was marred by the killing of Meredith Hunter by a security guard from the Hells Angels.",
        "answer": "The Rolling Stones"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Gone With the Wind was re-released in 1961 in part to re-take the US box office record from this film. Around the World in 80 Days and The King and I beat this film in all of its nominated Oscar categories except Best Special Effects, which it won in part for a scene created by playing footage of spilling water backwards. ABC has annually broadcast this film on Easter weekend since 1973. Cecil B. DeMille’s last film was, for ten points, what epic about the life of Moses?",
        "answer": "The Ten Commandments"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ten Commandments stars this man as Moses. He also starred in Ben-Hur, and he led the National Rifle Association for five years before his death in 2008.",
        "answer": [
          "Charlton Heston",
          "John Charles Carter"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Mohamed Hamdan Dagalo has led one of the groups in this conflict, a militia of Abbala and Baggara people known as “evil men on horseback.” The Justice and Equality Movement and the SLA are rebel groups opposed by government forces in this conflict. UN peacekeepers have been based in el-Fashir and Nyala during this conflict, in which hundreds of thousands of people have been killed. Omar al-Bashir carried out, for ten points, what crime against humanity in western Sudan?",
        "answer": "Darfur genocide or Darfur War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This militia, whose name loosely translates to “evil men on horseback,” has committed numerous war crimes during the Darfur genocide.",
        "answer": "Janjaweed"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At McGill, this man won several Wicksteed medals for gymnastics. Luther Gullick may have ordered this man to create a game, but Lambert Will's family disputes that. Legendary coach \"Phog\" Allen was himself coached by this man, who worked to get African- Americans the right to use university swimming pools. Neither dribbling nor free throws were part of this man's original rules. This Canadian invented a sport at the YMCA in Springfield, Massachusetts. For ten points, name this creator of the game of basketball.",
        "answer": "James Naismith"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Naismith spent ten years coaching basketball at this midwestern university, which won National Championships in 1952 under Phog Allen, in 1988 under Larry Brown, and in 2008 under Bill Self.",
        "answer": "University of Kansas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the Federal Baseball Club case, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr. stated that this law did not apply to Major League Baseball. It has been argued that this law’s namesake used it to lessen the blow of his ally William McKinley’s harsh tariff passed three months later. This law, strengthened by a 1914 act sponsored by Alabama Representative Henry D. Clayton, was ironically often used to break up labor unions in the late 19th century. For ten points, name this 1890 law intended to limit monopolies.",
        "answer": "Sherman Antitrust Act of 1890"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1948 Federal court case against this production studio, whose logo includes a lone mountain, changed the way film distribution worked in the U.S. after the studio was found in violation of the Sherman Antitrust Act.",
        "answer": "Paramount Pictures Corporation 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a Fiorello La Guardia-planned ticker-tape parade, this man was handed a brown bag with 10,000 dollars according to his wife, Minnie Ruth Solomon. This athlete claimed “Hitler didn’t snub me—it was our president who snubbed me\" after not receiving a telegram from sitting president Franklin Roosevelt. Minister of War Production Albert Speer [[SHPAY-uh]] claimed this man's accomplishments should lead to a ban on Black athletes in the Olympics. For ten points, name this sprinter, whose victory at the 1936 Olympics dismantled “the myth of Aryan supremacy.”",
        "answer": "James \"Jesse\" Owens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jesse Owens led a delegation of athletes in an attempt to get Jimmy Carter to lift the U.S. boycott on the 1980 Olympics which were held in this city.",
        "answer": "Moscow 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1993, an expert in this activity named Nigel Short created the PCA after cutting ties with an international organization. One man refused to participate in a 1975 World Championship in this activity because he espoused a first-to-ten wins schedule rather than a first-to-five wins schedule. In 1972, this event’s championship was held in Iceland and billed as a contest between the U.S. and the U.S.S.R., because it pitted Boris Spassky against Bobby Fischer. For ten points, name this game, whose leading grandmasters include Fabiano Caruana and Magnus Carlsen.",
        "answer": "Chess"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Russian World Chess Champion was the number one player in the world for the first time at age 20 in 1984 and was number one for nearly twice as many months as any other person in history.",
        "answer": "Garry Kasparov"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Husband set this song to \"Hephzibah\" [[HEP-zeh-bah]], while William Walker set this song to the \"New Britain\" tune using shape notes. The wretchedness discussed in this song may represent writer John Newton's realization of his wickedness as a slave trader. This song was published in Olney Hymns and was often used by Baptist ministers in the South during the Second Great Awakening. For ten points, name this Christian hymn whose opening line says that the title entity \"saved a wretch like me.\"",
        "answer": "\"Amazing Grace\""
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "\"Amazing Grace\" has been frequently performed by this social justice folk artist known for her original song \"Diamonds & Rust\" and for leading the crowd in “We Shall Overcome” at the March on Washington.",
        "answer": "Joan Baez"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man regarded Johnny Torrio as a mentor and William Hale Thompson as a business partner. A Baltimore hospital treated this man's neurosyphilis with one of the first- ever doses of penicillin. The Justice Department convicted this man for tax evasion, leading to his replacement as \"boss\" by Frank Nitti. Seven North Side Gang members died by this man's order in the 1929 Saint Valentine's Day Massacre. For ten points, name this Prohibition-era bootlegger and leader of the Chicago Outfit.",
        "answer": "Al Capone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Bureau of Prohibition agent, portrayed in film and television as an incorruptible crime fighter, led the so-called \"Untouchables\" in their effort to bring down Al Capone.",
        "answer": "Eliot Ness 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. Jimmy Claxton was perhaps the first person to successfully breach this regulation despite being promptly fired a week later. After speculation that Armando Marsans and Rafael Almeida broke this regulation, managers assured the public that \"they were as pure white as Castile soap.\" Branch Rickey and Bill Veeck both attempted to break this regulation, which was successfully broken when both Larry Doby and another player appeared on rosters. Jackie Robinson was the first player to break, for ten points, what regulation in Major League Baseball?",
        "answer": [
          "Baseball color line",
          "Baseball color barrier",
          "descriptions about how Black baseball players were prohibited from playing in the MLB"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This MLB team was the last to integrate due to resistance from owner Tom Yawkey. Other controversies surrounding this team included Bill Buckner's error during the 1986 World Series.",
        "answer": [
          "Boston Red Sox",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character is enticed by a sign to \"Join the Army and See the World\" and dies in the jungles of Vietnam in an underground protest film by Whitney Lee Savage. Margaret Thatcher labelled the European Parliament with this fictional character's name due to its perceived ineffectiveness. Despite making a short appearance in Plane Crazy, this character and his paramour first appeared in the short film Steamboat Willie. Walt Disney originally voiced, for ten points, which mascot of the Disney corporation?",
        "answer": "Mickey Mouse"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fredo claims he betrayed his brother due to being sent to run a \"Mickey Mouse nightclub\" in which gangster drama film revolving around the actions of the Corleone family?",
        "answer": "The Godfather"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite playing for the Browns, Joe Gedeon earned a lifetime ban for knowledge of this event. Former federal judge Kenesaw Mountain Landis ignored an acquittal of eight men during a faulty trial concerning this event and banned the defendants from one sport. Despite having a .375 batting average and committing zero errors, \"Shoeless Joe\" Jackson was banned for his alleged involvement in this event. Owner Charles Comiskey's poor wages led to, for ten points, which baseball scandal where a team threw the 1919 World Series in exchange for money?",
        "answer": [
          "Black Sox Scandal",
          "descriptions which include the White Sox throwing the World Series"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Earlier, Kennesaw Mountain Landis struck down a civil suit brought by the newly created \"Federal League\" against the MLB, which the Federal League brought to court using which 19th century antitrust act?",
        "answer": "1890 Sherman Anti-trust Act"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Many performers in these productions, which had a second-act olio, cribbed material from a New Orleans vendor named Old Corn Meal. Fixed roles in these productions included Mr. Tambo, Mr. Bones, and the interlocutor. A popular group that staged these productions was named for Edwin Pearce Christy and incorporated the music of Stephen Foster. For ten points, name this genre of racially charged 19th-century live variety shows in which performers often wore blackface.",
        "answer": "Minstrel shows or minstrelsy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1859, Virginia Minstrels troupe leader Daniel Decatur Emmett wrote this song, whose common version urges listeners in the title place to \"look away.\"",
        "answer": "\"Dixie\""
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The JFK Assassination",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Texas city in which Kennedy was killed.",
          "answer": "Dallas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Marine officially charged by the Warren Commission with shooting Kennedy.",
          "answer": "Lee Harvey Oswald"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nightclub owner who killed that assassin.",
          "answer": "Jack Ruby"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Lady who wore her bloodstained dress at Lyndon Johnson’s inauguration.",
          "answer": "Jacqueline or Jackie Kennedy Onassis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clothier whose silent film of the shooting is the most complete record of the event.",
          "answer": [
            "Abraham Zapruder",
            "Zapruder film"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Unknown woman who may have also filmed the shooting, nicknamed for her attire.",
          "answer": "Babushka Lady or synonyms, like Babushka Woman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas Governor wounded in the shooting.",
          "answer": "John Connally"
        },
        {
          "question": "Police officer shot and killed 45 minutes after Kennedy by the same killer.",
          "answer": "J.D. Tippit"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Saladin",
      "prompt": "In the life and times of Saladin, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country, whose city of Tikrit was the birthplace of both Saladin and Saddam Hussein.",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egypt-based dynasty founded by Saladin after the fall of the Fatimid caliphate.",
          "answer": "Ayyubid dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of Middle Ages religious conflicts, the third of which ended with Saladin’s victory over Christian forces.",
          "answer": [
            "Crusades",
            "Third Crusade"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The holy city defended by Saladin in that conflict.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "The English king who signed the Treaty of Jaffa with Saladin, calling a truce to end that conflict.",
          "answer": "Richard the Lionheart or Richard I"
        },
        {
          "question": "The type of payment collected in England to fund that conflict against Saladin, consisting of a 10% tax collected by bishops.",
          "answer": [
            "tithe",
            "tallage"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "July 1187 battle near a twin-peaked volcano where Saladin captured Guy of Lusignan [loo-sin-yon], triggering the aforementioned conflict.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Horns of Hattin"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in modern northern Israel, captured in that conflict by the freed Guy of Lusignan.",
          "answer": "Acre"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The “Rammer Jammer” cheer is performed by this team’s fans and its Million Dollar\nBand. All-American linebackers from this school include Cornelius Bennett, Derrick\nThomas, and DeMeco Ryans. Despite having star quarterbacks like Ken (20 pts) ",
        "Stabler and\nJoe Namath [NAY-muth], this team lacked a Heisman winner until Mark Ingram in\n2009. This SEC team’s most recent national championship win came in (10 pts) ",
        "2012 over Notre\nDame. They play in a stadium named in part for “Bear” Bryant and contest the Iron Bowl against\nAuburn. For 10 points, name this team, nicknamed the Crimson Tide."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alabama Crimson Tide",
        "Alabama",
        "Crimson Tide"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This conflict was called a “war without an enemy” by William Waller, who spent most of\nit fighting against Hopton's Cornish army. Incidents in this war included the Battle of\nChalgrove Field, where John Hampden was fatally wounded, and the defense of Turnham\nGreen by the trained bands of (20 pts) ",
        "London. This war's outcome was decided at the Battle of\nNaseby, where the “Oxford Army” was smashed by the (10 pts) ",
        "Roundhead cavalry of the New\nModel Army. For 10 points, name this 17th century conflict in which the Long Parliament\ndefeated Stuart royalists."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "First English Civil War",
        "English Civil",
        "English Civil War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This song’s music video, which depicts the newspaper headline “ELVIS JOINS THE\nARMY,” is set in a suburban American household. This song’s mention of (20 pts) ",
        "Psycho is\naccompanied by the signature violin screeches from that film. This song opens with the line\n“Harry Truman, Doris Day, (10 pts) ",
        "Red China, Johnnie Ray,” while its chorus notes that the title\nphenomenon “was always burning since the world’s been turning.” For 10 points, name this song\nby Billy Joel that lists various historical events."
      ],
      "answer": "We Didn't Start the Fire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A launch title for this system featured the first appearance of Professor E. Gadd and\nallowed the player to stun enemies with a flashlight before sucking them up with the\nPoltergust 3000. During development, this system was codenamed (20 pts) ",
        "“Dolphin”. After the\nfailure of the Dreamcast, Sega released Super Monkey Ball for this console. This system\nused a popular wireless controller called the (10 pts) ",
        "WaveBird, though it was criticized for its\nproprietary miniDVD format. Its exclusive games include Luigi’s Mansion and Super Smash\nBros. Melee. For 10 points, name this Nintendo console succeeded by the Wii."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nintendo GameCube",
        "GameCube",
        "NGC",
        "GCN"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This problem was first described by RAND Corporation members Merrill Flood and\nMelvin Dresher, and it was formalized by Albert W. Tucker. A computer tournament\ninvolving this problem was won by a four-line program written by Anatol (20 pts) ",
        "Rapaport\nnamed “Tit-for-Tat,” as described in Robert Axelrod’s book The Evolution of (10 pts) ",
        "Cooperation. A variation of its iterated version is called the “peace-war game”. For 10 points,\nname this scenario from game theory in which two criminals in separate jail cells are given the\nchoice of remaining silent or betraying their partner."
      ],
      "answer": "the prisoner’s dilemma"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Supporters of this team are known as “Kopites” [CO-pites] and sing along to Gerry and the Pacemakers’ cover of “You’ll Never Walk Alone.” 96 of its fans lost their lives in the Hillsborough Disaster and are the subject of a memorial outside (20 pts)",
        "Anfield. This team contests the Merseyside Derby with Everton and have won the English First Division 18 (10 pts)",
        "times. Last summer, they signed Mario Balotelli to help replace the departing Luis Suarez. For 10 points, name this soccer team managed by Brendan Rodgers and captained by Steven Gerrard."
      ],
      "answer": "Liverpool Football Club"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One version of this game was coded for free by intern Wes Cherry. Another version of this game, as taught by Andr’e de Staercke, includes a “Devil’s Six” (20 pts)",
        "row. That version of this game was published as an app by former Secretary of Defense Donald Rumsfeld in 2016, was named for Winston Churchill, and uses two (10 pts)",
        "decks. The goal of this game is to move all cards from the field and deck onto four foundations, starting with the Aces. Klondike is a popular form of, for ten points, what single-player card game?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "solitaire",
        "Churchill solitaire before mentioned",
        "Klondike solitaire before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This song’s final line was sometimes changed in performance to say that Jimmy Carter’s “got the answer.” This song references the Swampers of Muscle Shoals, and features the line “Now Watergate does not bother me, does your conscience bother you?” Written as a response to Neil Young’s (20 pts)",
        "“Southern Man,” its writer claimed that the line “Boo! Boo! Boo!” meant that he did not actually love Governor (10 pts)",
        "George Wallace. For ten points, name this Lynyrd Skynyrd song about a Southern state “where the skies are so blue.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Sweet Home Alabama"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party negotiated with Adolph Joffe for aid on the condition that this party allied itself with a rival; that alliance ended in the April 12th incident. The confiscation of contraband cigarettes from a 40 year old widow sparked the 2-28 (20 pts)",
        "massacre carried out by this party. In January 2016, this party lost a presidential election to the Democratic Progressive Party’s candidate Tsai Ing-Wen. This party was founded shortly after the (10 pts)",
        "Xinhai Revolution by Song Jiaoren and Sun Yat-Sen. For ten points, name this Taiwanese political party, founded in 1911 in China by Chiang Kai-Shek."
      ],
      "answer": "Kuomintang or KMT"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man played Luis Fernandez, a POW along side Michael Caine’s Captain John Colby, in 1981’s Victory , inspired by the “Death Match” played in Start Stadium in Ukraine. This athlete, who never lost a match while playing alongside Garrincha, remains the only player to win three (20 pts)",
        "FIFA World Cups. He was declared a “national treasure,” preventing a transfer to Europe from Santos for 18 years before he joined the NASL’s (10 pts)",
        "New York Cosmos. For ten points, name this legendary Brazilian forward, widely considered the best soccer player of the 20th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Pele or Edson Arantes do Nascimento"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work claims that religion is necessary to support political prosperity and notes that “the jealousy of a free people ought to be constantly awake” against the “insidious wiles of foreign influence.” This work draws an analogy between the interdependence of the (20 pts)",
        "north to south and east to west, arguing that decisions must be made as one nation. This speech cautions against the influence of European foreign powers and of the dangers of (10 pts)",
        "political parties. For ten points, name this work, which was published rather than delivered as a speech, near the end of the first U.S. president’s term."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Washington’s Farewell Address",
        "descriptive answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, James Dalyell’s attempt to ambush one side’s leader prompted the Battle of Bloody Run. During this conflict’s siege of Fort Pitt, Jeffrey Amherst used smallpox-infected (20 pts)",
        "blankets as a weapon. Popular myth holds that colonists were barred from settling west of the Appalachians following this conflict, which supposedly prompted George III to issue the Proclamation of (10 pts)",
        "1763. For ten points, name this revolt of native American tribes in the Great Lakes region, led by an Ottawa chief."
      ],
      "answer": "Pontiac’s Rebellion or War, Uprising, etc."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one role, this actor is shot many times before falling face-first onto a cake, walking into a bear trap, and falling off of a boat. This man, who played Officer Nordberg in the Naked Gun films, won the 1968 Heisman trophy while playing for (20 pts)",
        "USC and became the first player to rush for 2,000 yards in an NFL season. A In 1994, this man hired Robert Kardashian and Johnnie Cochran as (10 pts)",
        "defense attorneys. The book If I Did It was supposedly written by, for ten points, what running back who was acquitted of murdering Ron Goldman and his ex-wife, Nicole Brown?"
      ],
      "answer": "Orenthal James “OJ” Simpson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An early version of this work uses the phrase “waiting in the weeds,” later changed to “waiting in the wings.” In this work, a boy sings in French, then recites a poem on his ninth (20 pts)",
        "birthday to his father. The protagonist of this work is told to “talk less” and “smile more” by the antagonist, who later laments that “the world was (10 pts)",
        "wide enough” for both himself and the title character after they duel at Weehawken. For ten points, name this Lin-Manuel Miranda musical about the first treasury secretary, who was killed in a duel with Aaron Burr."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hamilton: An American Musical",
        "“Alexander Hamilton” before “French” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At one of these places, police captain Johan Mahieu failed to prevent a concrete wall from crushing civilians; Mahieu was later convicted of manslaughter for his role in the Heysel disaster. After misassigning blame in the wake of the (20 pts)",
        "Hillsborough disaster at another of these structures, the Sun newspaper was banned from the city of Liverpool. White Hart Lane, another of these structures, was demolished in August 2017, so (10 pts)",
        "Tottenham Hotspur’s temporary home is now Wembley. Old Trafford and Anfield are other examples of, for ten points, what European sporting venues for teams like Manchester United?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "European football stadiums",
        "Belgian football stadiums before “Hillsborough” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Donald Richie claimed that this country’s early films were limited by a live narrator whose comments caused directors to be too subtle. A director from this country commented on its post-war economy in a film where a woman is accused of stealing money to buy a (20 pts)",
        "washing machine. In another film from this country, the title warriors defend a rural village from bandits after being united by (10 pts)",
        "Kambei. This country relied more on Western film after its domestic production was disrupted by the 1923 Great Kanto earthquake. For ten points, name this country where Akira Kurosawa created Seven Samurai."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Japan",
        "Nippon",
        "Nihon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician included tracks like “Sonnet for Sister Kate” and “Sonnet for Caesar” in a twelve-part suite based on the work of William Shakespeare. Paul Gonsalves played a 27-chorus solo in the middle of “Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue” at the 1956 Newport (20 pts)",
        "Jazz Festival, where this bandleader was begged to stick to a curfew. Juan Tizol and saxophonist Johnny Hodges played in this man’s orchestra. Billy Strayhorn’s (10 pts)",
        "“Take the ‘A’ Train” was a theme song of, for ten points, what jazz pianist and composer of “Mood Indigo” and “It Don’t Mean a Thing (If it Ain’t Got That Swing)” who led the Cotton Club Orchestra?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Duke Ellington",
        "Edward Kennedy Ellington"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A film produced during this war depicts a leader who is jailed by Marcas the blacksmith. The Hello Girls operated in this war, as did the farmerettes. During this war, a mysterious explosion that was suspected to be sabotage occurred at (20 pts)",
        "Black Tom Island. Charles Lathrop Pack ran a War Garden Commission in this war, for which “wheatless Wednesdays” and “meatless Tuesdays” were created. The (10 pts)",
        "Zimmerman Telegram helped push the U.S. to declare war in, for ten points, what war in which the lost propaganda film The Kaiser, the Beast of Berlin was produced?"
      ],
      "answer": "World War I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Peace activists during this conflict included Betty Williams and Mairead Corrigan, who shared a Nobel Peace Prize for founding the Community of Peace People. Attacks in this conflict included an ambush at Narrow Water Castle near Warrenpoint. “1 (20 pts)",
        "Para” gained notoriety in this conflict for the Ballymurphy Massacre and the Bogside Massacre, the latter of which became known as (10 pts)",
        "“Bloody Sunday.” The 1998 Good Friday Agreement ended, for ten points, what conflict in Northern Ireland?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Troubles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Twenty-eight years after winning two medals at this event, Alfr´ed Haj´os won a silver medal for stadium design. George Averoff requested white marble from Mount Penteli to refurbish a stadium for this event, which was organized by (20 pts)",
        "Pierre de Coubertin. Stamata Revithi illegally competed in, and Spyridon Louis won, the first-ever (10 pts)",
        "marathon, which was invented for this event. The Panathenaic Stadium hosted, for ten points, what athletic competition that revived an ancient Greek tradition?"
      ],
      "answer": "1896 Summer Olympic Games"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One band from this country helped popularize distortion in rock music when they sliced their amp with a razor to record the song \"You Really Got Me.\" While performing in Des Moines, Iowa, one musician from this country (20 pts)",
        "bit off the head of a dead bat. Another musician from this country was assassinated by Mark David Chapman. Bands from this country such as The Kinks were part of a 1960s (10 pts)",
        "\"Invasion\" from this country to the United States. For ten points, name this country, home to rock bands such as Black Sabbath, The Rolling Stones, and the Beatles."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom or UK",
        "Great Britain",
        "England"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first capture of a foreign ship by a U.S. Navy vessel occurred during this conflict, when the USS Delaware trapped the privateering vessel La Croyable [[kroi- YAH-bluh]] in Great Egg Harbor. The massive bribes requested to meet (20 pts)",
        "Talleyrand during the XYZ Affair led to this conflict. The Convention of 1800, hosted by Consul (10 pts)",
        "Napoleon Bonaparte, ended this two-year conflict and affirmed U.S. neutrality. For ten points, name this undeclared naval war between the United States and France during John Adams’s Presidency."
      ],
      "answer": "Quasi-War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was banned from sports at Columbia University after he used the assumed name Henry Lewis to play professionally. Mayor Fiorello La Guardia appointed this man parole commissioner of New York in the last year of his life. This man was the first living person to appear on a (20 pts)",
        "Wheaties box and the first MLB player to have his number retired. This man claimed to be \"the luckiest (10 pts)",
        "man on the face of the earth\" in his retirement speech to a packed stadium in New York. For ten points, name this Yankees first baseman who died from a namesake neuromuscular disease."
      ],
      "answer": "Lou Gehrig 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Following his death, this musician was worshipped as a god and later a saint at the Yardbird Temple in San Francisco. In 2018, this musician's long-lost album Both Directions at Once was recovered. A Jazz Hall of Famer, this man received a posthumous Grammy in (*) 1982 for his album Bye, Bye Blackbird. With Cannonball Adderley, this musician played the (*) saxophone for Miles Davis's landmark album Kind of Blue. For ten points, name this influential jazz saxophonist, who recorded the albums Giant Steps and A Love Supreme."
      ],
      "answer": "John Coltrane"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was precipitated by the response to the Bhola Cyclone, which killed half a million people, leading Maulana Bhashani to call for one prime minister’s resignation. Pakistani president Zulfikar Ali Bhutto orchestrated the (20 pts)",
        "Delhi Agreement, which ended this conflict. Under President Yahya Khan, Pakistani forces began this war after committing Operation Searchlight, a mass killing of (10 pts)",
        "Bengali citizens. For ten points, name this armed conflict which led to the sovereignty of a nation with capital at Dhaka."
      ],
      "answer": "Bangladesh Liberation War or Bangladesh War of Independence"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man compared the extinction of civilization to that of a species in his 1910 Romanes lecture Biological Analogies in History. A late 1880s winter killed much of this man's cattle, forcing him to abandon his ranching venture at Elkhorn. With his son, (20 pts)",
        "Kermit, this man headed a namesake expedition with the Smithsonian, collecting over 11,000 animal specimens and authoring African Game Trails. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this U.S. president, whose saving of a cub led to the creation of his namesake stuffed bear."
      ],
      "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt Jr. or Teddy Roosevelt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this conflict, the Dikla and Yamit outposts were established in a territory that was occupied for fifteen years by this war's winner. This conflict erupted a few weeks after the closure of the Straits of Tiran to shipping, and it included the confused attack on the (20 pts)",
        "USS Liberty. Yitzhak Rabin disobeyed orders from Moshe Dayan and advanced into the Gaza Strip during this war, in which the Sinai Peninsula and West Bank was seized by the (10 pts)",
        "IGF. For ten points, identify this June 1967 clash between Israel and three Arab states, named for its brief duration."
      ],
      "answer": "Six-Day War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler of this name presided over the \"moderate decade\" and the \"progressive biennium,\" both named for the party in power. One ruler of this name ordered the execution of her court rival Hugh le (20 pts)",
        "Despenser. That ruler of this name allied with Roger Mortimer in a rebellion against her husband, Edward II. Along with her husband, a ruler of this name (10 pts)",
        "patronized the voyages of Christopher Columbus. For ten points, give this name of the Castilian queen who united Spain by marrying Ferdinand of Aragon."
      ],
      "answer": "Isabella"
    }
  ]
}